[Music]
Hello everyone. Welcome to this short
session on what's new in PowerBI
embedding for developers. My name is
Niko Chimitan and I am a software
engineer in the business central team.
And I'm going to present to you some new
features that we have developed for
PowerBI embedding with some bonus that
you as a partner and as a partner
developer can use for your own
integrations. So my um presentation is
structured in two parts. I'll start by
talking to you about what we did as new
uh improvements for the PowerBI embed
experience and then I'll show you a
short demo on how it looks like versus
what it looked like in the previous
versions and then I will go on to talk
about the user control host page type
which is a new feature we have
introduced in the latest Business
Central 2025 release wave
1. So talking about the PowerBI embed
improvements, we have an improved user
interface that just looks nicer, feels
nicer, and makes the reports that you
introduce into business central shine
embedded into our pages. We also use
these already in the Microsoft code
because we think it's the best way to
present reports to the user. And as you
know, we had a lot around 70 to 80 new
reports included in Business Central um
in the last few waves. So these also are
going to take advantage of these
improvements and it will just looks
nicer inside the business central UI. So
I will quickly show you how this looks
like in practice. Um how it looks in
today's production or yesterday's
production if you prefer versus the new
version of Business
Central. So I have now switched to
Business Central. This is the old
version of Business Central. I just want
to show you the difference between the
user experience when showing for example
the finance report that we have
introduced in business central a couple
of ways ago. So this is how it looks
like in 25 version 25 of business
central. You see that the report is
going to look nice in a couple of
seconds when it loads. But the UI around
it is just a bit too heavy. Why do we
need a delete button for a report or an
edit button? Um so this kind of um is
also the way you are probably doing
embedding and um control addins as a
partner but as you can see it it it's
okay um but it's not perfect. So this is
what we decided to improve on to make
the experience really great and shiny.
So now I will switch and I will change
tab and this is now Business Central in
the preview version 26. So you all uh
are going to be able to use this
version. And as you can see, I have now
uh the same PowerBI reports in my RO
center. So let's open the same finance
report and see how it looks
like. So you can all appreciate the
difference. Right now we have a very
nice UI around. There's no buttons that
really don't have a meaning in this
context. The margins around the reports
are also nicer. The titles show with a
more let's say balanced space. It was
taking way too much space in the older
version. And of course, you get still
all the very nice goodness from being
inside the business central page, which
means the controlladin reflows nicely
and this takes the space necessary. You
can also bookmark this page of course in
case you want to reach your report
faster next time with fewer clicks. So
this is how we have applied the new uh
user control page type to our PowerBI
reports. And you can of course do the
same by um using the user control page
type for your own embedding experience
of PowerBI reports as a developer. And
that's very simple to do. We also have
examples for these in
aka.ms/bct. So you can go have a look
and at how um the new user control host
page type
works. So this concludes my short demo
about the PowerBI embed improvements.
But I mentioned the user control host
page type. What is this? Well, um it's a
new page type as you probably have um
have gotten from my presentation, but
it's something we introduced in AL. So,
it's just the uh AL property page type
has one more value. And it's very simple
to use really because a lot of the
things and a lot of the controls for
example and triggers that don't really
apply to a control adin have been
removed to this page type which means
you don't get all these complications.
you don't get for example uh on after
get record triggers and things like that
because they just don't make sense in
the context of a user control host. So
um it's that also means it's very easy
to uptake. It's very easy to use in your
own code and it gives just this nice UI
which is um optimized for any control
edin. One more thing is that we have
more improvements planned for this page
type which means um stay tuned and be
sure that um you will get more goodness
out of this new feature.
So I will quickly show you the developer
point of view on how to use from AL the
user control host page
type. So now I switch to my visual
studio code and as you can see I have
just um my small PTE and I have one AL
file which is a card page. This is the
way you would embed or you would use
user control in a older version of
Business Central. You would just have a
card page that contains a user control.
In my case, I'm just using the webpage
viewer um just as an example, but of
course this also works exactly the same
for your own partner created user
controls. And you can see that I can
have actions for example um in my page
and I have a few properties on top for
example a source table um and whether
the record insertion is allowed and
things like that.
So um this is how you would do it in the
past and this is also the way that gives
the um kind of weird experience that I
showed you before with PowerBI, right?
So with this you would get the edit
button on top. Even if you say insert
allowed false, you will still get the
plus button um in the page and that's
not really what you want. So now we'll
do some light
coding in the coming 30 seconds. I'll
transform this into the new page type
user control host.
And the first thing I need to do is of
course changing the page
type. The moment I do that, the compiler
shows some warnings and it basically
tells me that a few of these properties
are not really supported in the new page
type. For example, there's no source
table for a user control host. And that
also means that insertion, modification,
and deletion are not really a thing.
They don't really make a lot of sense in
this context.
One more thing we don't support yet but
we are considering um maybe to work on
is actions. So actions are not supported
in a user control host. That's because
the whole space of the page is taken by
the user control itself rather than by
the actions. U but of course if you
think we should support them in the
future you know what you can do. You can
go always go to
aka.msbcid and let us know what you
think about this. But for my demo, let's
just remove the
actions. And as you can see, now my code
compiles. And let's actually try it out
immediately. So my extension is now
published. So I'll move back to business
central and let's see how it looks
like. So I have now switched to my
business central environment in the
version 26 preview. And this is the
sandbox environment where I just
uploaded my extension.
So as you can see there is a user
control host demo here which I have just
bookmarked. Um and this points to the
new page that I have just created. As
you can see the page loads nicely and we
have of course the uh controls to
bookmark the page. So I can bookmark and
remove it from the bookmarks as I've
done. But we also have controls to just
make the page larger and it just reflows
and behaves very nicely um in the new
page type. We have of course the titles
and everything as I showed you before
and no additional control or clutter
that you don't really need. For example,
there's no plus button to add new
records. Um, and no additional controls
really. So, um, yeah, as you can see,
this is exactly the experience you can
get with your own custom control addin
if you u are developing one. Otherwise,
um, you can just use this with the
business central uh control adins for
example the PowerBI host as well. So,
that concludes my short demo on the user
control host page
type and actually concludes my whole
presentation for this session. So, thank
you for your attention and I hope you
enjoy Business Central 2025 release wave
1.